<sequence_demo>
    <vertical_demo>
        <html_demo>
            <h3>Introduction to SQL</h3>
            <p>
                <a href="https://youtu.be/wxFmiRwXcQY" target="_blank">
                    Watch on YouTube
                </a>
            </p>
            <p>
                This video provides an introduction to the SQL query
                language. SQL, like the relational model, has been
                around for decades and supports a many billion dollar
                market.
            </p>
            <p>
                The first thing you might be wondering is how you
                pronounce it. Is it "SQL," or is it "sequel"? My
                friends in industry tell me that "sequel" is the in
                pronunciation, so that's the one I'll be using. Now SQL
                is supported by all major commercial database systems.
                It has been around a long time and it is a standardized
                language.
            </p>
            <p>
                The standard started out relatively simple but over the
                decades it's really ballooned. There are currently
                thousands of pages in the SQL standard. But the essence
                of the language, which is what we'll be learning in
                these videos, is still relatively simple. We will be
                learning primarily the SQL2 standard also known as SQL
                92 along with some constructs from the SQL3 standard.
            </p>
            <p>
                When SQL is used, it can be used in a database system
                interactively through a graphical user interface or a
                prompt so you type SQL queries or commands and you get
                results back, or SQL can be embedded in programs. So,
                the most common use is to embed SQL in programs but for
                the demos in our videos, naturally, we'll be submitting
                queries through a GUI interface.
            </p>
            <p>
                The last thing I wanted to mention about SQL is that it
                is a declarative language. That means that in SQL,
                you'll write pretty simple queries that say exactly what
                you want out of the database, and the queries do not
                need to describe how to get the data out of the
                database.
            </p>
            <p>
                The language is also based on relational algebra, and I
                hope you've watched the relational algebra videos.
            </p>
            <p>
                Now, the declarative nature of SQL leads to the
                component of the database system called the query
                optimizer to be extremely important.
            </p>
            <p>
                What the query optimizer does is it takes a query
                written in a SQL language and it figures out the best
                way, the fastest way, to execute that on the database.
            </p>
            <p>
                Now let's talk briefly fully about some terminology and
                the commands that are in the SQL language.
            </p>
            <p>
                There's two parts of the language, the Data Definition
                Language or DDL, and the Data Manipulation or DML.
            </p>
            <p>
                The Data Definition Language includes commands to create
                a table. We saw that in a previous video. It also
                includes commands to drop table and to create and drop
                other aspects of databases that we'll be learning about
                in later videos, such as indexes and views.
            </p>
            <p>
                The Data Manipulation Language is the language that's
                used to query and modify the database. So in the SQL
                language the Data Manipulation Language includes for
                querying the database, the select statement and then for
                modifying the database: an insert statement, a delete
                statement, and an update statement. There are many other
                commands in SQL for indexes, constraints, views,
                triggers, transactions, authorization, all of which
                we'll be learning about in later videos.
            </p>
            <p>
                For now, let's just take a look in a little more detail
                at the select statement which is really the bread and
                butter of the SQL language and it's what we use to query
                the database.
            </p>
            <p>
                So the select statement consists of three basic clauses.
                There's the SELECT clause, the FROM clause and the WHERE
                clause.
            </p>
            <p>
                The best order to think of these actually, is first the
                FROM clause, then the WHERE and then the SELECT and just
                the basic idea is that the FROM identifies the relations
                that you want to query over, the condition is used to
                combine the relations and to filter the relations. And
                finally, the SELECT tells you what to return.
            </p>
            <p>
                Now, if you're familiar with relational algebra, this
                expression here, this SQL query, is equivalent to the
                relational algebra expression that you project the set
                of attributes A1 through AN.
            </p>
            <p>
                And then you select and, by the way, it's different from
                this select here. In fact, this selection corresponds to
                the WHERE. You select the condition on the cross-product
                of the relations that are listed in the from clause. So
                that's the equivalent in relational algebra.
            </p>
            <p>
                And the last thing I wanted to mention is that, as you
                know, the relational query languages are compositional.
                That means when you run a query over relations, you get
                a relation as a result. So the result of this select
                statement is a relation. It doesn't have a name but the
                schema of that relation is the set of attributes that
                are returned. We'll learn much more about the SELECT
                statement in future videos.
            </p>
            <p>
                In conclusion, the SQL language is very prominent.
                <ul>
                    <li>It's supported by all major commercial database
                    systems.</li>
                    <li>It's been standardized over time.</li>
                    <li>It can be used through programs.</li>
                    <li>It can be used interactively and</li>
                    <li>it's a declarative high-level language whose
                    foundations are based on the relational
                    algebra.</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
        </html_demo>
    </vertical_demo>
</sequence_demo>
